Guide to the Collection on Enslavement in Cuba MSS.569
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Priest's Formal Declaration of Baptism of Emilion Esteban, a Freed Person, 1861-12-23 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  Emilio Esteban, the son of Sebastiana, was baptised on a March 28th. The note also states there was an oral judicial procedure between Sebastiana, represented by Jose Bruzon, and Ysabel Peres, to determine Emilio Esteban's status. The baptismal record is retrieved as proof of his free status.
- Contract in Guanajay between Felis Bambul and Laborer Vicente Vega from China, 1868-05-26 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  Government Department of Guanajay, Felis Bambul, 28 year old laborer from Canton (China), entered into a contract Vicente Vega for two years. According to the contract, Vega was to be paid a salary of eight pesos.
- Cuban License Issued by Vicente Molina Giving Permission for Five Congolese Enslaved People to Travel by Train, 1845-10-12 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  Enslaved people listed are: Pedro Criollo; Jose and Joaquin Lucumi; Cristobal from Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); and Florencio Congo. They were sent to Wajay to work in construction under the command of Jose Maria Peres. Document is signed by Governor Leopold O'Donnell granting the travel license.
- Cuban License Giving Permission for 36 Enslaved People to Travel by Train, 1845-10-31 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  Cuban license to travel freely by train to work on a sugar plantation. Enslaved people include: Antonio Criollo; Jerman; Francisco; Camilo; Hepomuceno; Cirilo; Domingo; Palomo; Francisco; Prospero Criollo; Isidro; Miguel Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); Matilde; Canuta; Ynes; [illegible name]; [illegible name]; Serefina; Maria Francisca; Dominga; Joaquina Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone); Maria de la Cruz; Andrea; Ignasia; Francisca Carabali; Damiana; Gregoria from Conga; and Julia. Document is signed by Governor Leopoldo O'Donnell.
- Document from Spanish Officials to Cuban Government Regarding Fine for Enslavers of Escaped Enslaved People, 1863 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  Document was written in Aranjuez, Spain during the Presidencia del Consejo de Ministerio de Ultramar and addressed to the Captain General of Cuba Domingo Dulce y Garay, who signed it upon receipt in Havana. The document discusses a fine of 30 pesos for owners of escaped enslaved people.
- Labor Contract Issued for Felipe Alvares Lozano and Dolores Castillo, 1852-09-01 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  Contract valid for a year between the laborers Felipe Alvares Lozano and Dolores Castillo (from Canarias) with Pedro Lopes. They contract states they were to be paid 4 pesos for doing domestic labor. The contract is signed by Salvador Carrillo, the deposit's (escrow) administrator and Miguel de Cárdenas y Cárdenas, chief of the commission.
- Labor Contract issued for 28 Enslaved People, 1852-08-31 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  Enslaved people include Arturo Garcia Perez, Ignacio Perez Martin, Antonio Cabrera de la Cruz, Domingo Lopes de Lopes, Juan Antonio Medina, Augustin Martin Sanches, Jose Maria Guerra Hernandes, Alejo Acosta, Juan Remedio Rodrigues, Juan Delgado Pinto, Nicolas Sanches, Juan Ventura, Jose Rodriguez, Jose Gabriel Ortega, Clemente Perez Hernandes, Ysidro Estrella Bentura, Luciano de la Coreya y Esposito, Juan de la Cruz Bello, Augustin de la Cruz Bello, Jose Hernandez, Portirio Luis Sanchez, Francisco Perez Martin, Viciente Diaz, Franco Perez, Mateo Carpio, Jose Manuel Remedio, and Geronimo Hernandes. Most of the listed persons originate from La Palma, La Victoria, Güimar and Santa Ursula, all in Tenerife. Another name appears crossed out in the list, possibly Ysidro Llamas; next to his name is a note that says he was on a different ship.
- Identity Paper for Luis in Puerto Rico, 1868-12-31 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  This document identifies 3 years old Luis, son of Firmina, enslaved by Sebastian Viñas in the neighborhood of San Felipe, vicinity of Arecibo (Puerto Rico). The document is signed by Ramon Viñas as the commissioner.
- Neighborhood News Bulletin on Miguel, an Enslaved Man Arrested for Robbery, 1879-11-25 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  In Matanzas, Miguel, enslaved by José Sainz, was apprehended and sent to prison for having hurt and stolen two pesos from Tomás, who was enslaved by Joaquín Robledo.
- Baptismal Declaration for Luis from Congo and Ricardo from Macua, Enslaved by Alejandro de Castro, 1839-06-09 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  Both enslaved by second lieutenant Alejandro de Castro, Luis from Congo was 17 years old, and Ricardo was 12. De Castro was their godfather.
- Birth Declaration for Miguel, Born to Freewoman Agueda Valdes, 1869-07-05 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  Document issued in Havana. Miguel was the son of Agueda Valdes. His father was unknown. His godmother was Manuela Martinez Rubio.
- Baptismal Declaration for Juan of Lucumi Origin, 1836-05-08 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  Document issued in San Salvador de la Prensa Barrio del Serro. Juan, of Lucumi origin, was enslaved by Pedro Martirn Rabell, his godfather, Alejo, was also enslaved by Jose Calasano Bilardebo.
- Birth Notice for the Child of Two Enslaved people, Nestor and Ramona, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  The document indicates that the father, Nestor, is from Congo and the mother, Ramona, is from Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone). Both parents were enslaved by Leon de Martiartu. The son, Nemesio, was declared as a legitimate child and his godmother, Ynes Martiartu, was a free woman.
- Request to Have a Newborn Child of an Enslaved Woman and Unnamed Man Baptized, 1852-10-22 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  Petition to the local priest of Cerro to baptize the enslaved son of Ynes, also enslaved by Francisco A. Cabañas. The name of the son is illegible.
- Statement of Baptism for a Congolese Enslaved Person who Belongs to the "Commission of the Railroad", 1836-03-27 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  Statement issued in San Salvador del Cerro documenting the baptism of Pablo, a person of the Congolese nation. The godfather is listed as Zeferino Carabali, who was to pay the rights for the ceremony. Signed by Domingo Alvarez.
- Manuscript Concerning the Capture of Escaped Enslaved People, 1868-05-05 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  The document concerns the escape of Luis, an enslaved person from Congo, and Anastasio, another enslaved person, both captured by Simon Garcia in Canasi. Their enslaver was Dolores Pebles de Pimienta. The document notes they were sent to the deposit of the maroons, and is addressed to the governor of Matanzas.
- Declaration that the Sacred Sacrament is Being Given to an Enslaved Person, 1847 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  The enslaved person, Aguenda, is described as Black criolla, daughter of Fumasa (surname illegible) and enslaved by Ygnacio de Arrieta. The godmother's name appears to be Maria Anta (possibly Antonia) Carabo.
- Birth Notice for the Child of an Enslaved Mother, 1877-12-05 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  The child, Francisco Santiago de la Trinidad, was son to Sixta, criolla, enslaved by Alejandro S. Juste. The godparents were Carlos Alfonso and Merced Vercuses (uncertain).
- Birth Notice for Merced Candelaria, 1847-04-11 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  This document describes the birth of Merced Candelaria on February 2, 1847. Merced's mother was named Eusebia de Torre, her father was unknown, and both Merced and Eusebia's control over their lives was inherited to Fercia de Torres. Merced's godmother's name was Trinidad Pastrana, criolla enslaved by Concepcion Miranda.
  This document was produced in San Salvador del Cerro.
- Statement on Martina Abasi, circa 1860s (Box 2, Folder 65)
  Martina Abasi, a free woman of color of Carabali origin, is identified as the godmother of emancipated people.
- Birth Notice of the Child of Juana Albarez, circa 1850s (Box 2, Folder 66)
  Note on the birth of Jose de los Santos, the child of Juana Albarez, a free woman of color, on All Saints Day. The child is the grandchild of Antonio Albarez and Rosalia Carrosa, also free people of color, and the godchild of Anselmo Garcia and Ysabel Angel, both identified as criollo. The father is unknown.
- Birth Notice of Maria Manuela, 1877-01-20 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  Note on the birth of Maria Manuela, to Emilia Dias (born Guines), maternal grandmother Eusebia Dias, and godmother Dominga Valdes, in Cerro.
- Baptism Notice of Pastoria Maria del Rosario, 1862-06-14 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  Notice of the baptism in Cerro of Pastoria Maria del Rosario, a criolla child born on March 30, 1862 into enslavement. She was the daughter of Polonia, a criolla woman, and an unknown father. Both parents were enslaved by Ygnacio de Vildosola. The godmother of the child is listed as Asunsion, a criolla woman enslaved by Josefa de Osmal. The document is signed by Nieves Gonzalez de Vildosola, administrator and heiress of Ygnacio de Vildosola, and addressed to the local priest of Cerro.
- Birth Notice of Serafin Urvano de Jesus, and Proof of Baptism of José, 1864-07-10 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  Notice of the birth of Serafin Urvano de Jesus on May 25, 1864 in Habana. Serafin was the legitimate son of the bachelor (bachiller) Rafael Pelaez, from Havana, and Ysabel Maria Hernandez, born in Managua, godchild of Serafin Pacheco, knight of the royal order of King Carlos III. A signed statement follows declaring proof of baptism of José, an emancipated seventeen-year-old Congolese person, formerly enslaved by Colonel Antonio Garcia Rizo. José was also the godchild of Manuel, a person enslaved by knight Serafin Pacheco.
- Neighborhood News Bulletin Describing a Robbery, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  Manuscript news bulletin announcing the robbery that allegedly happened to Camilo Macua, an emancipated man. He claimed his identification papers and money were stolen.
  A transcription of this document is avaialable by request.
- Birth Notice of Maria Laurecia, 1877-07-04 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  Notice of the birth of Maria Laurencia, in the community of Cerro. Lucrecia was the daughter of Vicenta, a criolla woman, and an unknown father who was enslaved by J. Godinez. The child's godmother was Maria Rincheta, a criolla woman enslaved by Sofia Perran.
- Manuscript Concerning Two Enslaved People Not Listed on Ship Manifest, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
  Manuscript concerning two enslaved people at Cabo Yndio named Ynes and Raimunda, both of Lucumí origin, not listed on ship manifest. Place and year of issue is unknown.
- Birth Notice of Arnalda, 1847-05-13 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  Notice of the birth of Arnalda, a criolla girl. Arnalda is the legitimate daughter of Nestor from Congo and Ramona from Ganga (now known as Sierra Leone), both enslaved by Leon de Martiartu. Her godmother is Josefa Martiartu.
- Manuscript Concerning Eulogio, an Emancipated Congolese Person Pursued by Law Enforcement, 1846-09-04 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  According to the document, Eulogio, an emancipated man, had run away since he was afraid of the punishments foremen were giving to him. He was captured, had his body examined in search of any marks that would serve as evidence of said punishments, and after not having found any sigfniciant marks, was held and placed at the disposal of the governor in Matanzas.
- Emancipation Document for Five People, 1886-10-09 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  Emancipation document for five people in Bolondron: Guadalupe, Silvestre, Ricardo, Ruperto, and Eduardo. Among the causes for emancipation are listed "of mutual agreement", "out of grace," and indemnification.
- Manumission Document for Higinio Guillermo, 1860-10-09 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  Manumission document for Higinio Guillermo, a boy in Habana born to an enslaved woman named Juana Paula. Higinio Guillermo's father is not named. Higinio Guillermo's former enslaver was María de Jesús Meza. The document was witnessed by Manuel García, Antonio Fernández and Felipe Maria Soya.
- Death Certificate for Domingo, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  Death certificate for Domingo, a man described as an escaped enslaved person originally from Asia. Domingo died from fever at the age of 30 at the Hospital de Caridad de San Felipe y Santiago on August 23, 1874. The document is dated December 23, 1776, but the year is likely incorrect.
- Emancipation Document for Five Persons, 1881-01-31 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  Issued in Matanzas. The emancipated persons were Maria Nicolasa, born in Cuba, formerly enslaved by Enrique García and Oña; Valentín, of Lucumí origin, formerly enslaved by Socorro de Armas; Gregoria, criolla, formerly enslaved by Juan G. Lavin; Luisa, formerly enslaved by Oña and sisters; and Matilde and her daughter Perfecta, criollas, formerly enslaved by Micaela Leiva.
- Notice that an Emancipated Man was Seen in a Havana Warehouse, 1868-06-23 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  The man located in Havana was Juan Macías, formerly enslaved (then emancipated) by Ygnacio de Cárdenas in Matanzas. The document is signed by Manuel Y. Madrigal.
- Birth Notice of Angel Custodio, 1851-10-26 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  In the vicinity of Cerro, on October 2nd, Angel Custodio was born to Damiana Escoto, born in Cuba, and Rafael Galarraga, Lucumí, all enslaved by José Antonio de Galarraga. The godparents were José Antonio Cárdenas and Andrea. The document is also signed by Maria Lusia Meza de Galarraga.
- Birth Notice of Maria Micaela Garcia, 1898-04-26 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  In the vicinity of Cerro, María Micaela García was born to Micaela García. María's maternal grandmother was Federica Piedra, and her godparents were José Matilde Cordovés and Carlota Cordovés.
- Birth Notice of Francisca Beatriz, 1838-12-09 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  On July 27, 1837, Francisca Beatriz was born to José de Zayas Basan, born in Wajay, and Ana de Pabia, born in Cuba. Francisca Beatriz' paternal grandparents were Pablo de Zayas Basan and María de Jesús Sanmartin. Her maternal grandparents were Agustín and Bernarda Acosta. Her godparents Agustín Ferrera and Francisca Valdes.
- Birth Notice of Maria Ca[ndel]aria, 1847-04-17 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  On February 2, Maria Candelaria was baptized. She was legitimate daughter of Antonio Vidal and Asuncion Dias, both born in Havana. Her paternal grandparents were José Vidal and Caridad de Laya. The maternal grandparents were Francisco Dominguez and Rosario Diaz. Her godmather was Luisa Martine.
- Birth Notice of Calletana, 1848-08-20 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  This document is a birth notice of a child, Calletana, who was likely enslaved. Her godmother's name was Luisa. The document was issued in Cerro.
- Birth Notice of Aparicio, Ganga, on the Aurelia Feliz Schooer (Goleta), 1844-07-28 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  In the Villanueva station of the Camino de Hierro (railroad), a child, Aparicio, of Ganga origin, was born on the goleta Aurelia Feliz. The child's godfather was Leoncio, of Lucumí origin. The document is signed by M. Machado.
- Manuscript of Priest Presenting Two Criados for Domestic Labor, 1836-06-05 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  The priest authorized for Pedro and Pio to be enslaved as servants for Bernardo de Abas. The document is signed by Francisco Enriquez.